<?xml version="1.0"?>

<HELPFILE>
    <TOOL>getxform</TOOL>
    <BRIEFLY>Extract a transform between coordinate systems in a teldef file</BRIEFLY>
    <DESCRIPTION>
    This tool extracts a FITS transform file specifying the transform between
    two coordinates systems in a teldef calibration file. The extracted transform
    may then be used by the imagetrans or applyxform tools.
    </DESCRIPTION>

    <PARAMETERS>
        <PARAM>
            <NAME>teldef</NAME>
            The teldef calibration file specifying the coordinate systems.
        </PARAM>

        <PARAM>
            <NAME>from</NAME>
            The name of the initial coordinate system. These have three letter names
            in all caps such as "RAW", "DET", or "SKY".
        </PARAM>
        
        <PARAM>
            <NAME>to</NAME>
            The name of the transformed cooridnate system.
        </PARAM>
        
        <PARAM>
            <NAME>image</NAME>
            If this is true the transform will be given in terms of pixel 
            coordinates - i.e. the first pixel will have coordinates (1,1). 
            Otherwise the transform will assume the first pixel has the
            coordinates specified in the teldef file. If the transform will be
            used unmodified in the imagetrans tool, then you should set this to 
            true. You may want to set this to false if you will use the transform
            in applytransform or if you would like to modify the transform
            to account for windowing in terms of the teldef coordinates.
        </PARAM>
        
        <PARAM>
            <NAME>mjdref</NAME>
            The Modified Julian Day when the mission time is 0.0.
            This is used when calculating aberration.
        </PARAM>
        
        <PARAM>
            <NAME>aberration</NAME>
            If true, the effects of the motion of the Earth around the Sun will 
            be added to a transform involving sky coordinates.
        </PARAM>

        <PARAM>
            <NAME>outfile</NAME>
            The FITS file which will contain the transform specification.
            This file is typically used as in put to another tool which applies 
            the transform.
        </PARAM>
    </PARAMETERS>

    <EXAMPLES>

    </EXAMPLES>

    <SEEALSO>

    </SEEALSO>


</HELPFILE>