<?xml version="1.0"?>

<HELPFILE>
    <TOOL>combinexform</TOOL>
    <BRIEFLY>Creates or modifies a transform</BRIEFLY>
    <DESCRIPTION>
    This tool may be used to modify a transform or to create one. The resulting
    transform may be used as input to the imagetrans or applyxform tools.
    It has a simple command interpreter which allows you to specify a list of
    transforms which will be applied in order.
    </DESCRIPTION>

    <PARAMETERS>
        <PARAM>
            <NAME>outfile</NAME>
            The FITS file which will specify the resulting transform
        </PARAM>
        
        <PARAM>
            <NAME>command</NAME>
            <P>
            A list of commands specifying the transforms to be combined. If this 
            parameter begins with "@", then the rest of the parameter value is 
            treated as a filename. The commands will be read from this file one 
            per line.
            </P>
            
            <P>
            The following commands are available:
            trans(dx,dy) - translate by dx horizontally, and dy vertically.
            rot(angle) rotate counter-clockwise by angle degrees.
            scale(sx, sy) scale by a factor of sx horizontally, and sy vertically
            file(filename) read a translation from a FITS file. This file may be
            the output from another run of this tool or from getxform.
            </P>
            
            <P>
            For example:
            </P>
            <P>
            "scale(2,2)"
            results in a scaling by a factor of two.
            </P>
            <P>
            "trans(-10.0, -20) rot(30) trans(10, 20)"
            does a rotation of 30 degrees about the point (10,20).
            </P>
            <P>
            trans(100, 100) file(raw2sky.xform) trans(-50, -50)
            Applies windowing to the transform specified in the file raw2sky.xform.
            The resulting transform will be appropriate for an input image with the first
            100 pixels clipped off and an output image with the first 50 pixels clipped off.
            </P>
        </PARAM>
    </PARAMETERS>

    <EXAMPLES>

    </EXAMPLES>

    <SEEALSO>
        <P>
        <LINK>getxform</LINK>,
        </P>
    </SEEALSO>


</HELPFILE>